<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Kirill Nikitin&#39;s Personal Page on Kirill Nikitin&#39;s Personal Page</title>
    <link>https://nikirill.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Kirill Nikitin&#39;s Personal Page on Kirill Nikitin&#39;s Personal Page</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2025 Kirill Nikitin</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Private Information Leakage from Polygenic Risk Scores</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/publication/prs/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/publication/prs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My DYI EB-1A green card petition</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/post/greencard/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/post/greencard/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/i140.pdf&#34;&gt;I-140 petition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../files/i485.pdf&#34;&gt;I-485 petition&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/nikirill/eb1a&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;I-140 and I-485 LaTeX templates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;background&#34;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have recently received my U.S. green card after petitioning under the EB-1A category as an alien of extraordinary ability in sciences. The petitioning process was definitely convoluted, and I had to spend quite a bit of time navigating it. But I was able to prepare, file and get my petition approved without hiring a lawyer.
Probably, the most helpful thing in the process was to read other researchers&amp;rsquo; petition examples, which are only a handful online. So I have decided to post my complete petition with the hope that it can be helpful to anyone who would like to prepare their petition by themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am originally from Russia where I completed my undergraduate studies. After doing MS and PhD in Europe, I moved to New York on a J1 visa to start my postdoc. Being from Russia, I had been subject to administrative processing every time I had applied for a U.S. visa so, after my initial stamp expired, I could not travel outside the country anymore (administrative processing typically took several months and my postdoc position did not have the flexibility of working for months from abroad) so I needed the green card even to be able to travel to conferences abroad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I knew several people who petitioned for a green card with the help of various law firms. I did a profile evaluation with a couple popular firms but I did not find them particularly convincing (but I did find them pricey!). At the same time, a friend of mine, also a postdoc but in a different field, prepared and got approved for EB2-NIW without lawyers so I knew that it was feasible. So I decided to try the DYI route with the idea that I always could go back to lawyers if the task would turn out too hard. That was when I started studying any resources available online. The two examples online that helped me the most were the petitions and templates of Razvan Marinescu (2021) and of Andrey Solovyev (2012). My petition structure was primarily based on the example of Razvan Marinescu. I also found the Oscar&amp;rsquo;s Green Card Youtube channel useful, especially the interviews with other petitioners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://razvanmarinescu.github.io/green-card-I-140/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Razvan Marinescu&amp;rsquo;s petition and template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://andreychemist.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Andrey Solovyev&amp;rsquo;s petition examples and template&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@OscarsGreenCard&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Oscar&amp;rsquo;s Green Card Youtube channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why-eb-1a&#34;&gt;Why EB-1A&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was initially looking into EB2-NIW, as my profile was not outstanding&amp;mdash;I had around 300 citations and five publications, two out of which as the first author, although all the publications were in great venues in my field. But the backlog meant that, even if I was approved, I would be able to get the green card only in several years. Then, in the beginning of 2024, I learned that Apple had implemented a tiny piece of my research in their new iMessage protocol. So I figured that I could try to present it as a substantial contribution (&lt;em&gt;slightly&lt;/em&gt; exaggerating the impact) and apply for EB-1A. I also had fairly extensive reviewing experience so I could claim that too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The petition preparation took me about nine months of occasional evening and weekend work. It could definitely be done much but I wanted to make sure that I prepared the best petition I could, so I spent quite a bit of time reading, collecting evidence and rewriting parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;timeline&#34;&gt;Timeline&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May, 2024: Start studying the options and aim for EB-2 NIW&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;July, 2024: Decide to switch to EB-1A to avoid priority date wait&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;December, 2024: Exhibits are collected and the petition is mostly written&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;January, 2025: Start contacting potential support-letter writers and drafting the letters&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;March, 2025: All the support letters are received&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;ndash; &amp;ndash; &amp;ndash; &amp;ndash;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 1, 2025: Send my I-140 EB-1A petition with the I-907 Form for Premium Processing (15 business days processing guarantee)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 4, 2025: I-140 petition is received by USCIS (Nebraska Service Center)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 9, 2025: Case is being actively reviewed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 10, 2025: I-140 petition is accepted&lt;br /&gt;
&amp;ndash; &amp;ndash; &amp;ndash; &amp;ndash;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;April 24, 2025: I-485 petition is received by USCIS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May 2, 2025: Request for biometrics letter appeared in the online account&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;May 21, 2025: Biometrics appointment, the status changed to &amp;ldquo;Case being actively reviewed&amp;rdquo; (the interview was waived)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;, 2025: Green card approved&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;hellip;, 2025: Green card received&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My personal opinion is that if you have either a surefire case &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; a complicated situation, then getting assistance from an attorney can be useful and might significantly cut down your preparation time. But if you are a scientist with a reasonable but not outstanding profile (basically, like mine), you might have a better chance of getting approved by preparing the petition yourself, as you can write a personalized petition, instead of inserting your information into a lawyer&amp;rsquo;s template. In either case, you will need to do most of evidence gathering yourself, so knowing what to search for helps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer: I am not a lawyer and none of the information here is a legal advice.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-140&#34;&gt;I-140&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started with choosing criteria from &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.uscis.gov/policy-manual/volume-6-part-f-chapter-2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;the extraordinary-ability list&lt;/a&gt; on the USCIS website which I could potentially claim. One needs to satisfy three criteria to meet the requirements but it is possible to claim more. As long as evidence for any three criteria is accepted and the officer concludes that the overall profile has substantial merit, the petition will be accepted. I chose to claim four (criteria 3, 4, 5, and 6) in case the officer disagrees with one, although the evidence for the published material about my work (criterion 3) was rather thin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recommend starting your petition with a high-level overview of your work&amp;rsquo;s impact and its relevance to the US. I started with explaining the themes in my work and cited relevant executive orders (even though the new administration retracted several of them). Then, I described each of the themes in detail but in the language that was accessible to a non-expert. The arguments that I used were the use of my work in real-world systems, the existence of follow-up works by other researchers, potential practical implications of the results, the importance of the addressed problems, and the inclusion of my paper in seminar curricula at other universities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The evidence for the authorship of scholarly articles was the ranking of the venues where I had published, the number of publications, and the number of citations. I believe that these numbers do not need to be very high, as long as the rest of the story lines up. I was able to find and screenshot every review that I had written (tedious) and used them as the judging evidence. I used the GoFullPage browser extension to screenshot the reviews. When I could find them, I also added the emails with the invitations to join the conference program committees or to provide an expert review. I also mentioned my membership in associations in the field but I did not claim them as a separate criterion, as they were not the ones that would qualify. For the published material in media, I briefly described the legitimacy of the media outlets and enclosed the screenshots of the articles. Finally, I corroborated most of the arguments in the petition with quotes from the support letters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;support-letters&#34;&gt;Support letters&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my opinion, the letters of support are the most crucial part of a strong petition. I got eight letters to be on the safe side but I would say that one needs at least four. Anecdotally, the recent USCIS adjudication guidelines instruct to favor letters by recommenders who either have collaborated with the petitioner or know their work reasonably well. The letters need substance in them, and the recommenders should be experts in their respective fields. Law firms sometimes suggest submitting without support letters but, frankly, this is simply to save their effort and time and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of my eight recommenders, two were my former research advisors, four were university professors who knew me and my work a little bit&amp;mdash;because we either had met at a conference, I had given a talk at their seminar at some point, or I had previously interviewed to work with them&amp;mdash;and two were applied scientists from a tech company that deployed a small piece of my research in its product.
Two recommenders offered to write their letters (I have excluded them from the posted petition above), and I drafted the remaining six that the recommenders later edited to their preference. I used the same standard structure for all the letters:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The introduction of how the recommender knew me / my work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Their professional biography (adapted from their website)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Description of one or two of my research projects, introducing the context first and then describing how my work filled the gap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commentary on either my publishing stats, conference reviewing, media articles, or the importance of my field of expertise to the US. I tried to justify why each recommender talked about prospective topics, e.g., one recommender was on the PC of a conference in my field in the same year as me, so it was easy to justify why they could speak for that&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conclusion reiterating that my permanent residency would be useful to the US.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;degree-evaluation&#34;&gt;Degree evaluation&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not sure if it was as important for EB-1 as for EB2-NIW but I got my foreign degrees evaluated by one of the approved services. The purpose was to have a proof of equivalency, e.g., that my Doctor of Sciences degree from Switzerland corresponded to PhD in the US. I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://foreigncredentials.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Foreign Credentials Service of America (FCSA)&lt;/a&gt; because I found them to be the cheapest&amp;mdash;I paid $85 for the equivalency report for my three degrees. I think that it took them two weeks to produce the report and the first version had some spelling errors but they got them fixed right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&#34;payment&#34;&gt;Payment&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to use separate credit-card authorization forms or checks for each fee. So, in my case, it was $715 filing fee + $300 asylum program fee for filing as a self-petitioner + $2,805 premium processing fee. Reddit insists on paying by checks, but if you have a credit card from a US bank, you should arguably be fine paying with it. I used an Amex card for I-140 and later a Capital One card for I-485 and both worked without an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;i-485&#34;&gt;I-485&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Filing the I-485 form is pretty straightforward. The extra work you would need to do is translating your birth certificate if it is not in English and doing the medical exam / searching for your vaccination records. I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://itrex.ru/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Itrex Language Services&lt;/a&gt; and paid an equivalent of $10 for a certified translation of my USSR-issued birth certificate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the medical exam, I ended up going to Family Medicine NYC (Dr. Eva Galstian) and paid $200 in cash for the exam itself. The tests got covered by my health insurance as I combined the visit with my annual physical. I do not think I would recommend them because they ordered antibody tests for the vaccines that I had records for but told me to re-vaccinate for the vaccines that I had antibody tests done elsewhere. If you are in the NYC area, I have also read about Vitastat Medical (Dr. Ken Truong) in Astoria and Dr. Xiaorong Yan in Flushing who charge $150 and $100, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Private Information Leakage from Polygenic Risk Scores</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/talk/prs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/talk/prs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Authenticated private information retrieval</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/publication/apir/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/publication/apir/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrity and Metadata Protection in Data Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/talk/thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/talk/thesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Replicated state machines without replicated execution</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/publication/piperine/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2020 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/publication/piperine/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Padded Uniform Random Blobs (PURBs)</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/project/purbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Dec 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/project/purbs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Most encrypted data formats leak metadata via their plaintext headers, such as format version, encryption schemes used,
number of recipients who can decrypt the data, and even the recipients’ identities.
This leakage can pose security and privacy risks to users, e.g., by revealing the full membership of a group of
collaborators from a single encrypted e-mail, or by enabling an eavesdropper to fingerprint the precise encryption
software version and configuration the sender used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We propose that future encrypted data formats improve security and privacy hygiene by producing
&lt;em&gt;Padded Uniform Random Blobs&lt;/em&gt; or PURBs: ciphertexts indistinguishable from random bit strings to anyone without
a decryption key. A PURB’s content leaks &lt;em&gt;nothing at all&lt;/em&gt;, even the application that created it, and is padded
such that even its length leaks as little as possible.
Encoding and decoding ciphertexts with &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; cleartext markers presents efficiency challenges, however.
We present cryptographically agile encodings enabling legitimate recipients to decrypt a PURB efficiently, even
when encrypted for any number of recipients’ public keys and/or passwords, and when these public keys
are from different cryptographic suites. PURBs employ Padmé, a novel padding scheme that limits information leakage
via ciphertexts of maximum length &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt; to a practical optimum of O(log log &lt;em&gt;M&lt;/em&gt;) bits, comparable to
padding to a power of two, but with lower overhead of at most 12% and decreasing with larger payloads.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducing metadata leakage from encrypted files and communication with PURBs</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/publication/purbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2019 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/publication/purbs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducing Metadata Leakage from Encrypted Files and Communication with PURBs</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/talk/purbs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jul 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/talk/purbs/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crux: Locality-Preserving Distributed Services</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/publication/crux/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/publication/crux/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CHAINIAC: Proactive Software-Update Transparency via Collectively Signed Skipchains and Verified Builds</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/talk/chainiac/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/talk/chainiac/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CHAINIAC: Proactive software-update transparency via collectively signed skipchains and verified builds</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/publication/chainiac/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/publication/chainiac/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Security of software-update systems</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/project/chainiac/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/project/chainiac/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Software-update mechanisms are critical to the security of modern systems, but their typically centralized design
presents a lucrative and frequently attacked target. In this work, we propose CHAINIAC, a decentralized software-update
framework that eliminates single points of failure, enforces transparency, and provides efficient verifiability of
integrity and authenticity for software-release processes. Independent &lt;em&gt;witness servers&lt;/em&gt; collectively verify
conformance of software updates to release policies, &lt;em&gt;build verifiers&lt;/em&gt; validate the source-to-binary correspondence,
and a tamper-proof release log stores collectively signed updates, thus ensuring that no release is accepted by clients
before being widely disclosed and validated. The release log embodies a skipchain, a novel data structure, enabling
arbitrarily out-of-date clients to efficiently validate updates and signing keys.
Evaluation of our CHAINIAC prototype on reproducible Debian packages shows that the automated update process takes
the average of 5 minutes per release for individual packages, and only 20 seconds for the aggregate timeline.
We further evaluate the framework using real-world data from the PyPI package repository and show that it offers
clients security comparable to verifying every single update themselves while consuming only one-fifth of the bandwidth
and having a minimal computational overhead.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Axiom - DTLS-based secure IoT group communication</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/publication/axiom/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/publication/axiom/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Collective Authority (Cothority) Framework</title>
      <link>https://nikirill.com/project/cothority/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://nikirill.com/project/cothority/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
